Guide to the Stanley Dance and Helen Oakley Dance Papers
Yale University Music Library
Papers of Stanley Dance and Helen Oakley Dance
1920-1998
MSS 62
Yale University Music Library
37
(85 containers)
The Papers of Stanley Dance and Helen Oakley Dance are an important resource for the study of 20th-century jazz history in the United States. Of particular interest are transcripts from interviews with a number of jazz musicians, a large selection of photographs, and sound recordings – many of which are unique. Most – but not all – of the material having to do with Earl Hines and Duke Ellington can be found in their respective series. Researchers are advised to examine other series for additional material.
Dance, Stanley
Dance, Helen Oakley, 1913-2001
Separated Materials
Approximately 50 non-rare commercial videotapes have been separated from the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open for research, with the exception of the sound recordings, which are currently in process.
Biographical / Historical
Stanley Dance (1910-1999) and Helen Oakley Dance (1913-2001) were jazz critics, writers and producers. They married in 1947, having met in New York years earlier, at which time Helen was producing jazz recordings for Irving Mills. Helen Oakley began her career by moving from her native Toronto to Chicago in the early 1930s, where she covered the jazz scene for the fledgling Downbeat magazine. She also founded the Chicago Rhythm Club, which hosted performances by the Benny Goodman Trio and Duke Ellington, among others. Oakley was also producing recordings for various jazz artists, which she continued to do in New York, for Irving Mills. In 1939, she began working for Duke Ellington. During World War II, Helen Oakley joined the Office of Strategic Services and worked in North Africa. After her military service, she moved to England and married Stanley Dance. She spent the next two decades raising a family, before moving to the US and continuing her writing and producing career.
Stanley Dance, born in England, first wrote about jazz in the French journal Jazz hot. After moving to the U.S., he wrote several books and contributed regularly to publications such as Metronome, Saturday Review, and Jazz Journal. Dance conducted interviews with dozens of jazz musicians, and these interviews constitute several of his books and articles. He had a particularly close relationship with Duke Ellington, with whom he prepared Music is My Mistress, Ellington's autobiography.
Arrangement
The arrangement of the Dance Papers relies heavily on the original order of the collection. The Papers are divided into the following series: I. Writings and interviews; II. Files, research materials, programs and posters; III. Clippings; IV. Photographs; V. Correspondence; VI. Materials related to Earl Hines; VII. Materials related to Duke Ellington; and VIII. Sound Recordings.
Related Materials
Interviews with Stanley Dance and Helen Oakley Dance can be found in the Duke Ellington Oral History collection, held by Oral History of American Music (OHAM) at Yale University.
Related Materials
Interviews with Stanley Dance and Helen Oakley Dance can be found in the Fillius Jazz Archive at Hamilton College.
Scope and Contents
The Papers of Stanley Dance and Helen Oakley Dance are an important resource for the study of 20th-century jazz history in the United States. Of particular interest are transcripts from interviews with a number of jazz musicians, a large selection of photographs, and sound recordings, many of which are unique. Most – but not all – of the material having to do with Earl Hines and Duke Ellington can be found in their respective series. Researchers are advised to examine other series for additional material.
Perhaps the greatest limitation of the Papers is the lack of material from Helen Oakley Dance's career before 1950. This likely has to do with her moves across the Atlantic, and time spent in military service. Researchers are advised to consult the oral history collections listed under Associated Materials.
- Writings and interviews, 1937-1998
  Scope and Contents
  The Writings and Interviews series contains both published and unpublished copies of articles, reviews, columns and liner notes. The vast majority of material was written by Stanley Dance; the small amount of material written by Helen Oakley Dance is labeled as such. There are a number of notebooks and memo books, most of which have identifying titles and/or dates.
  As both the Dances' published books rely heavily on oral history, the most significant material in this series can be found in the Interviews and Transcripts sub-series. Many of these interviews are unique, in that they don't appear to have been published or associated with a known oral history collection.
  - Articles removed from scrapbooks (Box 1)
    These newspaper and magazine articles were removed from scrapbooks and photocopied when the collection was initially acquired. There are several article written by Stanley Dance and Helen Oakley Dance, as well as interviews with and articles about the Dances. Also included are interviews with jazz musicians. Publications include Musical Express, The Daily Mirror, Melody Maker, East Anglian Daily Times, The Essex Chronicle, Jazz News and Downbeat. Additional news clippings about Stanley Dance have been added to this box.
  - "Lightly and Politely" typescripts
    Typescripts for "Lightly and Politely", a column that Stanley Dance wrote for Jazz Journal.
    - 1958-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1969-1972 (Box 2A)
    - 1973-1998 (Box 3)
  - Jazz Times typescript reviews
    - Book reviews (Box 3)
    - 1979-1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983-1989 (Box 4)
    - 1990-1997 (Box 5)
  - Saturday Review, published copies of "Recordings Reports", 1957-1972 (Box 6)
  - Music Journal, published copies of "Jazz" column, 1962-1977 (Box 6)
  - Music Journal, typescripts of articles and reviews, 1976-1978 (Box 6)
  - Drafts of various articles, 1968-1999 (Box 6, Box 6A)
    Includes typescripts for journals such as Hansen Publications, Jazz Journal, Stereo Review, Jazz Beat, and others. Publication is indicated by the initials of the journal in the upper right-hand corner of the typescript.
  - Reviews, liner notes, and articles written by Helen Dance (Box 6A)
    Includes one article from 1936. The remainder appear to be from the 1970's and 80's.
  - "Communications Through Effective Reading: 2nd Book" (Box 6A)
    Textbook published by Learn Inc. Contains an article written by Stanley Dance on page 54.
  - Concert reviews, 1968-1975 (Box 14)
  - Notebooks, 1967-1998
    Spiral-bound notebooks containing drafts of articles, reviews, and correspondence. Many have titles which are transcribed directly from the notebook cover and most have dates. Notebooks belonged to Stanley Dance unless otherwise indicated.
    - "1967" (Box 7)
    - "Mercer Tape Locker May 1975" (Box 7)
    - "Ellington - Time Life 1978" (Box 7)
    - "Misc 1978 Red Callender" (Box 7)
    - "Earl Hines Time-Life 1979" (Box 7)
    - "Billy May 1981" (Box 7)
    - "1982 Jazz Times etc" (Box 7)
    - "1983 Vegas Hines Memorial" (Box 7)
    - "1984" (Box 7)
    - "1984 Contd" (Box 7)
    - "1984 Various Noone Grissom" (Box 8)
    - "1984-85 Various" (Box 8)
    - "1985 Contd" (Box 8)
    - "1985 Various" (Box 8)
    - "Clark Terry 1985", "SS Norway", "Louis Bellson", "Ends With Quotes" (Box 8)
    - "Helen's Notes and SD Reviews 1986" (Box 8)
    - "HMD Notes Feb 86 Hines Liners" (Box 8)
    - "Hampy and March 1986" (Box 8)
    - "1986 JT and Liner Notes" (Box 8)
    - "DB List and SD Notes 1986" (Box 8)
    - "1987 LMR Liner Notes" (Box 8)
    - "1987" (Box 9)
    - "1988 Colin Noone Grover Mitchell" (Box 9)
    - "April 88 Various" (Box 9)
    - "Late 1988 into 1989" (Box 9)
    - "1988 June to June 1989" (Box 9)
    - "1989" (Box 9)
    - "1989-1990" (Box 9)
    - "1990" (Box 9)
    - "1990 Musicmasters" (Box 9)
    - "Oct 1990" (Box 9)
    - "The Duke's Men 1991" (Box 9)
    - "1991", "1992 McElroy's" (Box 9)
    - "1992 EH Notes to Lincoln Center" (Box 10)
    - "Reviews for April 1992" (Box 10)
    - "1993 - 1994" (Box 10)
    - "1994" (Box 10)
    - "1995-96" (Box 10)
    - "1996 2" (Box 10)
    - "1996 3" (Box 10)
    - "1997-1" (Box 10)
    - "1997 II" (Box 10)
    - "1997-2 Sacred Concerts Liner Notes" (Box 10)
    - "Live 1997" (Box 10)
    - "1998" (Box 10)
    - "Queen S", "Paul Bascomb", "Willie Randall", "Charlie Carpenter" (Box 10)
    - "Century Vault Grans Compilations" (Box 11)
    - "Mary Lou Williams", "Jimmy Smith", "Count Basie", "Buster Coorer", "Record Reviews" (Box 11)
    - "Earl Eulogies" (Box 11)
    - "Ellington" (Box 11)
    - "The Jaywalker CD" (Box 11)
    - "Notes for Stella Solaris Cruise etc" (Box 11)
    - "Ray" (Box 11)
    - "Notes on Contributors to Grove Dictionary of American Music", "Jimmy Cheatham Interviewed" (Box 11)
    - "Billy May I includes Willie Smith Story on EKE Journal" (Box 11)
    - "Tucker Patiassie Translation", "McElroy's" (Box 11)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 11)
    - "Clark Terry" (Box 11)
    - "Dizzy Gillespie" (Box 12)
    - "HND Notes" (Box 12)
    - "Quotes for HCF" (Box 12)
    - "Ellington Chronology" (Box 12)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 12)
    - "Al Gray", "Shorty Baker" (Box 12)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 12)
    - "Ray Charles" (Box 12)
    - "BOMC Ellington Notes" (Box 12)
    - "Helen's Notebook" (Box 12)
    - "Charlie Barnet Chapter VI" (Box 12)
    - "Charlie Barnet" (Box 12)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 12)
    - "Grove by Sam Rhino" (Box 12)
    - "Jazz Times" (Box 12A)
    - "Books" (Box 12A)
    - "Gene Ramey II", "Joe Williams", "Nat Pierce", "Intro", "Hines S-R", "Ellington Retrospect" (Box 12A)
    - "Night People" (Box 12A)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 12A)
  - Memo books, 1961-1987
    The memo books consist of notes taken during live performances, including dates/times, lineups, and tunes played. Also included are quotes, contact information for various people, and miscellaneous notes. Many of the memo books are titled and dated, but some are unlabeled. Most (but not all) appear to be in Stanley Dance's hand.
    - "1961" (Box 15)
    - "1966" (Box 15)
    - "Aug 66 Nov 66" (Box 15)
    - [untitled memo book] (Box 15)
    - "July to Sept 1964" (Box 15)
    - "1965 Hines Hodges Basie Sessions" (Box 15)
    - "1965 Monterey" (Box 15)
    - "1966", "10" (Box 15)
    - "Newport 1966" (Box 15)
    - "QTB" (Box 15)
    - "Final", "Late 1966" (Box 15)
    - "July 1967 to Sept 1st", "Duke Rainbowgrill", "Jimmy Mundy", "Basie Atlantic", "Hodges-Subway" (Box 15)
    - "Miami Beach Mexico 1967 Apl-July" (Box 15)
    - "March 67", "July 67", "Duke", "Jaywalker", "Cleanhead", "Joe Turner", "Edgar Burke" (Box 15)
    - "Newport 1968" (Box 15)
    - "Europe 68", "Duke", "Degas, etc." (Box 15)
    - "1967", "Rab Triple Play 1968", "N. Orleans" (Box 15)
    - "Dance", "S Francisco", "Rob Hines", "1968" (Box 15)
    - Sept. 1967 Ellington, Basie (Box 15)
    - "1968" (Box 15)
    - "December 68 to April 69", "MJR Solo", "Basie", "Earl", "Duke" (Box 15)
    - "April 1969 to May 26 1969" (Box 15)
    - "SF LA LV 1969 Sept 27" (Box 15)
    - "1969 NO" (Box 15)
    - "ESEFOI Son Duke '69" (Box 15)
    - "February 1970" (Box 15)
    - "June-Nov 1970" (Box 15)
    - "Nov 1970 May 1971" (Box 16)
    - "May 1971" (Box 16)
    - "March 1972 June 1972" (Box 16)
    - "Oct 71 March 72", "In Europe with Duke" (Box 16)
    - "Mewpal 1972", "Madison 1972", "June-August" (Box 16)
    - "Sept 1972 February 1973" (Box 16)
    - "LA, 7/1/73 10/10/73" (Box 16)
    - "Newport '73" (Box 16)
    - "Oct 73 March 74" (Box 16)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 16)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 16)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 16)
    - "April-July 1974 Newport" (Box 16)
    - "July 1974 to Oct 1974", "Colorado Carney" (Box 16)
    - "Oct 1974 June 1975" (Box 16)
    - "June '75 SS Rotterdam", "June 76 " (Box 16)
    - "1976 to 1977" (Box 16)
    - "1977-78" (Box 16)
    - "Newport 1978" (Box 16)
    - "NYC '85", "'84" (Box 16)
    - "RVL Dec '85" (Box 16)
    - "Books 86" (Box 16)
    - "Norway 1987" (Box 16)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 16)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 16)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 16)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - "Horton Plaza Directions" (Box 17)
    - [untitled notebook] (Box 17)
    - "Ikayi" (Box 17)
    - "Stanley Dance 1745 Bittersweet Vista, CA" (Box 17)
    - "Mexico" (Box 17)
    - "Skeets Marsh" (Box 17)
    - "Some Cotton Club, Hines" (Box 17)
  - Liner notes
    - 1960-1989 (Box 13)
      1980's folder contains liner notes from Benny Carter's 75th anniversary.
    - 1990's + Other (Box 14)
      Includes liner notes from the 1990's and from Time Life and SD Writings publications.
    - Earl Hines liner notes - Time Life (Box 14)
    - CD liner notes, 1972-1994 (Box 14)
      Contains three CD liner notes: "Jazz Connoisseur, A Name to Look Out For" (no date), "Back on the Street" by Earl Hines, Jonah Jones, Buddy Tate, and Cozy Cole (1972), and "Johnny Varro on Piano, Everything I love" (1994).
    - Liner notes for Duke Ellington (Box 14)
  - Interview transcripts
    The interviews included here fall into two general categories: interviews for oral history projects and interviews for future journalistic articles. The oral history project interviews are mostly typed and often do not include the interviewer's questions. Most average approximately 15 to 30 pages in length with some outliers. The article transcripts are generally shorter than the oral history transcripts and are formatted into paragraphs. The articles are occasionally structured as narratives of influential events in the musician's life.
    - Anderson, Ivy, 3/1/1973 (Box 18)
      Contains three interviews: Sonny Greer, Earl Hines, and Stanley Dance (?), speaking about Ivy Anderson.
    - Armstrong, Louis, July 1970 (Box 18)
      Contains several drafts of an interview transcript for an article.
    - Bach, Jean, 1988 (Box 18)
    - Bascomb, Paul, c. 1970 (Box 18)
    - Battle, Edgar, no date (Box 18)
      Two copies of an interview transcript and some handwritten notes.
    - Bellson, Louis, c. 1990 (Box 18)
      Interview transcript and draft of an article written after the interview.
    - Benson, George, 1967 (Box 18)
      Draft of an article.
    - Bert, Eddie, 1978 (Box 18)
      Two drafts of an article.
    - Bown, Patti, no date (Box 18)
      Two drafts of an interview conducted for an article.
    - Boyd, Bobby, no date (Box 18)
    - Brackman, Allie (Brachman), c. 1970 (Box 18)
    - Buckner, Milt, July 1973 (Box 18)
      Handwritten transcription of an interview conducted by Claude Battestini. Also includes a note written by Claude Battestini for Helen and Stanley Dance.
    - Buckner, Ted, c. 1976 (Box 18)
    - Callendar, Red, 1975 (Box 18)
      Interview transcript and a draft of the article written about the interview.
    - Cheatham, Jeannie, 3/14/1987 (Box 18)
      Interview transcript and draft of an article written about the interview.
    - Cheatham, Jimmy, c. 1987 (Box 18)
    - Clayton, Buck, 9/11/1972 (Box 18)
    - Cobb, Arnett, August 1978 (Box 18)
      Full transcript interview with Cobb also found in the Smithsonian Jazz Oral History Collection. Also contains two copies of a letter sent by Cobb's daughter, Lizette and a short article entitled "Reunion Blues" by Stanley Crouch.
    - Coltrane, Alice, no date (Box 18)
      Biography of Alice Coltrane.
    - Crawford, Ray, c. 1960 (Box 18)
      Transcript of an interview conducted by Robert Boss. Also includes a discography.
    - Dance, Helen Oakley, no date, 1984 (Box 18)
      Transcripts of two interviews: one conducted by Pat Willard (with hand-written notes), and another from CJRT-FM in Toronto.
    - Dance, Stanley (Box 18)
      Transcripts from an interview and two radio programs with Stanley Dance (1945 and 1955).
    - Driver, Wilson "Bill", c. 1972 (Box 18)
    - Edison, Harry, c. 1980 (Box 18)
    - Flanagan, Tommy, no date (Box 19)
    - Gillespie, Dizzy, July 1963 (Box 19)
      Two drafts of articles and an interview transcript.
    - Greer, Sonny, no date (Box 19)
    - Guy, Buddy, & Junior Wells, January 1975 (Box 19)
      Three drafts and a published copy of an article on both Guy and Wells. Published copy contains handwritten notes and edits.
    - Hall, Barrie Lee, Jr., 10/20/80 (Box 19)
    - Haynes, Cyril, no date (Box 19)
      Draft of an article. Interviewed by Jack Bradley.
    - Heard, J.C., c. 1985 (Box 19)
      Interview transcript and a draft of the article.
    - Henderson, Fletcher, 10/9/91 (Box 19)
      Transcript of Helen Oakley Dance speaking about Fletcher Henderson. "Requested by Willie Ruff at Yale" written on front page.
    - Hines, Earl, 1971 (Box 19)
      Two interview transcripts. One interview conducted by John Lax in 1971 for the Oral History Research Office at Columbia University.
    - Hodges, Johnny, c. 1965 (Box 19)
      Contains a draft of an article about Hodges. Author is unclear.
    - Jacquet, Illinois, c. 1985 (Box 19)
      Interview transcript and a draft of a biography written after the interview.
    - Johnson, Money, c. 1985 (Box 19)
    - Jones, Jonah, c. 1980 (Box 19)
    - Jones, Quincy, no date (Box 19)
      Two drafts of an article written for Metronome.
    - King, B.B., February 1967 (Box 19)
      Draft of an article and a published copy of the article from Jazz Magazine.
    - Lunceford, Jimmie, c. 1975 (Box 19)
    - MacDermot, Galt, c. 1980 (Box 19)
      Interview transcript and a draft of the article written after the interview.
    - Matthews, Onzy, c. 1970 (Box 19)
    - May, Billy, c. 1980 (Box 19)
      Contains a draft of an article about May. Author is unclear.
    - Mayall, John, September 1974 (Box 19)
      Draft and a published copy of the article written for Music Journal.
    - McShann, Jay, c. 1980 (Box 19)
    - Miller, Eddie, no date (Box 19)
      Interview conducted by Henry [], possibly for a radio broadcast.
    - Milton, Roy, c. 1980 (Box 19)
      Contains a transcript of an oral interview conducted by Helen Oakley Dance.
    - Minerve, Harold "Geezil", 1972 (Box 19)
    - Mingus, Charles, c. 1980 (Box 19)
      Two drafts of an article written on Mingus.
    - Mitchell, Grover, 1988 (Box 19)
      Interview transcript and a draft of an article.
    - Moore, Melvin, c. 1980 (Box 19)
    - Nance, Ray, 2/2/76 (Box 19)
      Two drafts of a short Ray Nance biography.
    - Noone, Jimmy Jr., 1985 (Box 19)
    - O'Farrill, Chico, c. 1963 (Box 19)
    - O'Neal, Hank, March 1988 (Box 19)
    - Otis, Johnny, c. 1975 (Box 19)
    - Page, Oran Thaddeus "Hot Lips", c. 1971 (Box 19)
      Draft of a biography.
    - Powell, Jimmy, c. 1978 (Box 19)
    - Ramey, Gene, September 1978 (Box 19)
      Contains full transcript of interview which is found in the Smithsonian Jazz Oral History Program.
    - Richards, Red, c. 1978 (Box 20)
      Draft of an article written on Richards.
    - Shier, Shelley, 1991 (Box 20)
    - Singleton, Zutty, 10/27/1972 - 11/14/1972 (Box 20)
    - Smith, Bessie, no date (Box 20)
    - Smith, Jimmy, c. 1980 (Box 20)
    - Tate, Buddy, 10/23/87 (Box 20)
    - Terry, Clark, c. 1980 (Box 20)
    - Turney, Norris, c. 1970 (Box 20)
    - Tyner, McCoy, c. 1970 (Box 20)
    - Vinson, Eddie, c. 1970 (Box 20)
    - Weston, Randy, c. 1970 (Box 20)
    - Woodyard, Sam, no date (Box 20)
- Files, research materials, programs and posters
  This series contains the Dance's files, which include published copies of articles, drafts for books and plays, research materials, programs and posters.
  Arrangement
  In this series, the materials have been kept in their original order.
  - Contracts with Mercer Ellington and Manheim Fox Productions (Box 21)
  - John Steiner, Chicago Defender abstractions (Box 21)
    Abstractions contain information regarding jazz articles, concerts, and news from issues of the Chicago Defender (1919-1929). Also includes two pages of correspondence with John Steiner.
  - Benny Goodman, list of unreleased material - to 1945 (Box 21)
  - Album catalogues for Vocalion and Relevant Records (Box 21)
  - Charlie Barnet, discography and list of arrangements (Box 21)
  - Repertoire lists for Time-Life recording project (Box 21)
  - Decca re-issue notes (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous drawings and certificates (Box 21)
  - Martin Williams correspondence and artricles (Box 21)
  - Helen Dance, Oren Jacoby film correspondence and notes (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 21)
    ca. 50 pages of hand-written notes. Various topics and musicians.
  - Decca recordings lists (Box 21)
  - Dance v. Jewell: copyright infringement court case 1978 (Box 22)
  - Helen Oakley Dance files (Box 22)
    Includes a list of recordings made from 1935-1937 in Chicago and New York, letters and a photo from Helen's time in the OSS, invitations from the White House, autobiographical info and an interview transcript, outline for a proposed book, correspondence with Smithsonian about Duke Ellington oral history project, and various newspaper articles and reviews.
  - Count Basie material (Box 22)
    Includes various promotional posters, concert programs, travel and concert itineraries, record company documents, and Basie memorial programs.
  - "Three Score" a quiz for jazz musicians, 1967 (Box 22)
    Published in Jazz Spectrum and The World of Swing.
  - Artist information file (Box 22)
    A reference file put together by Stanley Dance. Lists of recordings, clippings, and general notes are organized alphabetically by the name of the artist.
  - Notes on various jazz recordings, 1958-1984 (Box 22)
    Includes tracklistings, artist listings, and other notes.
  - "Night People" typescript draft (Box 23)
  - "Recent American Records for 1953-1959" (Box 23)
  - Transcography (Box 23)
    "A discography of jazz and 'pop' music issued on 16" transcriptions."
  - Transcriptions (Box 23)
    List of transcription discs by various jazz artists beginning in the 1940's.
  - Certificates: Outstanding Service to Jazz Education, 1999 (Box 23)
    Contains a copy of "Teacher's Manual, Test Bank, and Discography for Jazz Styles" by Mark C. Gridley.
  - Notes from Sammy Lowe (Box 23)
    Includes copies of lyrics and a page of correspondence.
  - "The Jazz Photographs of Charles Peterson" (Box 24)
    Draft for the book "Swing Era New York: The Jazz Photographs of Charles Peterson" for which Stanley Dance wrote the introduction.
  - Photographs for unpublished book, "Jazz Jungle" (Box 24)
  - Photo list of Duncan P. Schiedt (Box 24)
  - Charlie Barnet autobiography drafts (Box 24)
  - Savoy Ballroom concert posters (Box 24)
    Posters include artists such as Earl Hines, Ella Fitzgerald, Count Basie, Coleman Hawkins, Tommy Dorsey, among others. Many of the posters are photocopied.
  - File Organizer, 1994-1996 (Box 25)
    Contains Stanley Dance's files from this time period. Also includes a draft of a 1944 article from Metronome and copies of record catalogues from 1927.
  - "Stormy Monday: The T-Bone Walker Story" by Helen Dance (Box 25)
    Two unmarked drafts. Also includes discographies.
  - Drafts of "Sammy Lowe: Diary of a Black Musician" (Box 26)
  - "Bands at Lafayette Theatre Harlem Opera House Apollo Theatre 1931-1945" (Box 26)
    Appears to be photocopied from another source.